Hi, my name is Pearl Hodling, and I'm a senior in Kirkland House, and I'm here to ask you
to join me this Saturday from 10 to 2 for free pancakes from Henrietta's table in the MAC Quad.
Nine years ago, my dad was diagnosed with Parkinson's disease, a neurological disorder.
Though he, my family, and I have gone through many ups and downs, both physical and emotional, I finally found a way to help a definitive up.
I wanted to put on this event, Pancakes for Parkinson's, for a few years now, but I didn't get up the guts to do it until this year.
Thank you, Tal, for helping me to get over my procrastination and start building a positive spiral towards finding a care for Parkinson's disease.
All donations will go directly to the Michael J. Fox Foundation for Parkinson's Research, so please come between 10 and 2 this Saturday to enjoy Pancakes for a Good Cause. Thank you.
Hi, my name is Maureen Hilton and I'm a fellow student of this class and I work here at Harvard
College. I would like to invite you all to my positive psychology presentation which is next
Friday, May 9th at 2 p.m. in Harvard Hall. The main goal hoped for next Friday is to bring together
in one room people interested in positive psychology here at Harvard. This includes
Harvard administrators of all levels, the class's teaching staff, students, whether they are alumni
of past positive psychology class, a current student of this class, whether college or extension
school, or a student who hopes there's a positive psychology here in the future, and certainly anyone you would like to invite. Please let this be an opportunity for you to share your stories
and the reasons why this class has impacted your life.
In addition, to help the networking and socializing part of this gathering,
the Harvard callbacks will be singing.
The seniors who you may know, Gina, Skyler, and Kadar, will be singing their solos for possibly the last time here at Harvard.
And there will be free food.
Again, please feel free to bring, invite anyone you like, especially fellow students who are hoping there is another positive psychology course in the future. No RSVP is necessary, just come.
Because what will definitely leave a lasting impression on the Harvard administration is if together we create a little peak experience and fill a room of people
who come together for the promotion of positive psychology.
Please come next Friday, May 9th at 2 p.m. at Harvard Hall. Thank you.
I don't really know what to say, so I ask someone to say it for me.
I need your help. I'm so very nervous. What can I do?
Meditate. Thank you. Exercise. Now? You mean dance. Okay. Tell a joke. You tell a
joke. What else? Any suggestions? Hug someone. Good idea. At least 12 hugs,
right yeah anything else deep breaths okay good so it's okay to be nervous thank you
feel better already so this is for me the last class at harvard
world. Who else is in the same boat? Wow, your last class. What I'd like to do today
is summarize what we've gone through, some of the journey as much as possible. And what
I'd like to do is to share that, the responsibility of summarizing, to share it with you. So I'd
like to start with you thinking and reflecting about the course. In other words, we're going
to run the class today like a small intimate section, and afterwards I will go through
what I think are some of the highlights, main points from the semester. So I want to
start with a time in, an opportunity for you to reflect, and specifically I would like
you to reflect on the following things and actually write them down. So go over
your notes or go over your mental notes and write down at least two things that
were particularly meaningful or interesting for you from the semester. Whether it's something you heard in lecture, something you discussed in
section, something that you read, something that you talked about with your friends after
class and somehow was connected to your experience here. Anything or at least two things that
were personally meaningful and interesting to you. So this is the first thing. The second thing I'd like you to write down and you may have done it before, you may have written
it before, at least two commitments that you're making, two behavioral changes or attitudinal
changes, two commitments that you're taking upon yourself now that the semester is almost
over. So again two meaningful or interesting ideas at least and at least two commitments
whether it's in the form of rituals, attitudinal change or behavioral change.
So take just a few minutes to do that in a time in.
Okay, now what I'd like you to do and this is completely voluntary of course
is share some of the things that you have learned or at least one thing that you learned that was personally meaningful or interesting to you from the semester,
and if you feel comfortable, the one of the two commitments or both commitments that you've taken upon yourself
with the person next to you or with two people next to you.
So take just five minutes to share with one another one interesting or meaningful thing and one commitment or two.
Okay, okay. I hope you continue the rest of the day, the rest of your life sharing what you've
learned, what you are learning, how you're growing. Now what I'd like to do is hear some of you,
just talk about one thing, perhaps if you find found interesting or meaningful, it could be
directly from the class or something tangential but what was meaningful or
interesting for you this semester and we have some microphones spread around the
room so if anyone would like to be the first one to volunteer remember courage
is not about not having fear it's about having fear and going ahead anyway if
courage was about not having fear or would not be teaching this class?
I think for me, what most important thing was, was the idea of a self-concordant goal, not being frivolous or selfish, but actually being something that one should actively pursue
and can help the people around you more than by pursuing that which you're told to pursue.
Great. So essentially dissolving this divide between self and other.
And remember the Dalai Lama, how surprised he was when he came to the West and he heard that our word for compassion means essentially compassion toward others,
whereas Tsewe in Tibetan means compassion toward others and compassion toward oneself.
They go hand in hand, they're intertwined.
So identifying our self-concordant goals is very much about helping ourselves and ultimately making the world a better place. Wonderful, thank you.
I found the Roger Bannister story really meaningful to me, especially because now I know that nothing is impossible, even if scientists tell you things are impossible, you can still achieve them.
Right, you know, so often people tell us that it's impossible, you can't do it, and we have that voice in the back of our mind, those limiting beliefs,
whether it's limiting beliefs about how we can feel can feel and what we can achieve and what we what the Roger Bannister story does what it helps us to
do is chip away some of these limitations and understand our potential
thank you yes the day when you told the story about your grandmother and how she was able to still see so much beauty in the world after everything she had been
through was very very moving for me and that was really a unique experience to be so emotionally moved in this academic setting so that was very powerful and it
really made me reevaluate the way I look at my life in the way that I appreciate
the things that I have. Great, thank you. Thank you. I really like the idea that we
can get over things bad things a lot quicker than we would anticipate I just think that you know so often we treat ourselves with so much success with so much potential pleasure but I think you know this idea of going forward and that
will ultimately get over it if it doesn't work out is really important. Right yeah so you know just like when we achieve something good we go back to base level
and feel as we did before also when we fail and it's a real liberating feeling
to know that that we're resilient that we will recover. Thank you. For me it was
important to realize the balance between the rat racer and the hedonist. Finding the balance between short-term benefit and long-term benefit. Right, you know, so much of our life is about
either or. Either I'm a successful rat racer or I'm a hedonist who has given up essentially on
success. Whereas what we can very often do is reconcile the two, you know, eat the cake and
leave it whole, so it seems. Future benefits and present benefits in one. Thank you.
To seek to be known and not validated. The way you taught the class, opening up let's say each individual failure you had in your life, I found myself, my own
failures, they're different but they're the same. I felt less lonely.
thank you you know one what I shared I think the very first class here was what
Carl Rogers said which is what is most personal is Moses general because deep
down humanity is humanity is humanity and when we live in the world with the
desire to be known expressing ourselves that's I think when we can reach out most to others whether it's in a romantic relationship whether it's in
friendships whether it's in a classroom thank you yes one thing I'm going to take away from this class is to be conscious about being grateful because sometimes
I feel that you take for granted the people that you love the most to be grateful there's so many treasures of happiness of well-being all around us
and within us and the challenge is just to open our eyes to appreciate them yes
What was really amazing to me was how open others were not in the class, such as family or other friends not in the class, to also take on these changes in their life.
They didn't see it as some kooky self-help thing, but really as, oh yeah, maybe I should take note of all these things I'm grateful for in my life and other exercises.
Yeah, you know, this is paying it forward. Sometimes we're so afraid to talk about things that matter to us. And when we do, and when we're real, when we're genuine, when we express ourselves,
these things are contagious.
And we pay it forward, and then they pay it forward.
Thank you. Yes.
Before taking this class, I blamed my mood and my happiness a lot on what was going on around me and my circumstances.
And so taking this class has really helped me learn that circumstances really don't control your happiness level and that I have more of an active role in, like, how I feel.
Right. You know, remember one of the things we talked about is that,
at least I don't believe that things necessarily happen for the best.
You know, there are some times where there are bad circumstances, poor circumstances, hard circumstances.
The challenge, though, is how can we make the best of that which has happened, and we do have much more control over it than we think.
Yes.
the class allowed me so many times during almost every day to understand something as part of me
being human, as part of my permission to be human, rather than to consider it as my failings or something I wasn't doing well enough. So the permission to be human, I've repeated it so many
times and I'll continue to repeat it until use every last minute that I have to do it because it really is on so many levels the foundation of well-being and unfortunately too much in
our culture today what is going on is what i call the great deception where we think well everyone is doing great except for me so i'm going to pretend that i'm doing great too and then we
become part of that great deception reinforcing it the permission to be human yes um uh the whole
piece about perfectionism. I had never really seen myself as a perfectionist, and I think it was just kind of self-denial. So through the exercises in the course as well as, you
know, in the book and different readings that we've done, have really allowed me to explore
that and accept that and make proactive changes in my life to grow away from that.
Great. You know, perfectionism is, again, another thing that so many people hide because
because the perfectionist almost by definition doesn't want to show the weakness and as I mentioned in the class on perfectionism
for me that has been the most important in terms of my progression toward becoming happier, accepting failure as inevitable,
accepting that life is not a straight line but rather a spiral with ups and downs as long as the general trajectory is of improvement, growth and permission.
So for me, one of the things that really resonated was the idea of reframing the question.
At the very beginning, you spoke about the fact that there was a 21 to 1 ratio of negative to positive research.
And as someone who will be going into research and neurobiology,
it was really interesting just a reframing of a worldview to start thinking of, well, perhaps start looking at what is working in terms of research.
And so I'll take that with me into my academics. The importance of questions. Questions create our reality.
Remember the question of the children on the bus,
which most people completely missed.
Remember years and years of research that was done in inner cities
with at-risk populations where they missed the answer to how can we improve their lives.
They missed it because they did not also ask the positive question.
and it applies into every area of our lives as I'll talk about soon yes before I always
procrastinate that's my big problem for my academic not improved a lot so thank you very much
thank you um procrastination 70 percent of students in universities complain about
procrastination it's a huge issue and one of the ways to overcome it the best way to overcome it is to just do it just start remember the five minute takeoff
that's so important thank you yeah I was just really really impressed with that
reading that we read by Gilbert that was talking about how the good luck in your life and the wonderful circumstances you find yourself in are really your own making and by changing your outlook and your patterns you can really make a
difference in your happiness day-to-day. So many people lead lives and think well
only I didn't meet that person, if only this hadn't happened to me I would have been happy and understanding that so much of it is determined by our
perception is very empowering. What's been most meaningful for me has been
The fact that this class exists and that there's so many people interested in happiness because in this culture here at Harvard, we don't always get the chance to really think about it.
And as you've said, you're just reminding us of what we already know, but it's also letting us know that we're not crazy for knowing it.
Yeah, we're not. We're not alone.
And we need that reminder, and other people need that reminder. And by reminding other people, we also remind ourselves.
Thank you. Yes?
For me, it was the concept of integrity, because I think we're all honest people, but it's the little things, the times each day when we compromise our beliefs
or act in a way that doesn't align with how we think we should and that that really takes a toll on our self-esteem. And so the idea of being constantly aware of and maintaining our integrity,
I think really stands to help us feel better about ourselves because you know
when when we tell the truth we're communicating a certain message to ourselves when we express ourselves we're communicating a certain message to
ourselves and the message is my words count I count when we express I'm good
enough don't need to put on a facade or impress and that message was self
perception theory actually enhances how we feel about ourselves. Not to mention that it helps
interpersonal communication and the world would be a better place if more and more people acted
with integrity. Again, self and others divide and dissolve. Yes. One of the phrases that you shared
with us in your lectures that's really impacted me and I've actually embraced as a kind of personal mantra is learn to fail or fail to learn. There is no other way. And I kind of realized throughout
the course of this class what a perfectionist I have been and how much time throughout my life, my earliest memories, I've spent really torturing myself with anxiety and fear of
making a mistake. And to reframe that and really look at those inevitable moments where
I mess up as, you know, fuel for moving forward and as opportunities have been wildly liberating. So I thank you for that.
Thank you. The notion of learn to fail and fail to learn, as you know, it's my personal mantra as well, is very liberating. It's liberating within the context of a relationship,
within the context of our academic performance, within the context of an organization on every level.
And it's important to understand that there is no other way to learn, whether it's to draw a circle or to walk it's just part of life and if we accept it we're much
happier for it thank you Elizabeth what has been really meaningful to me in deciding what
concentration to pursue is the idea of happiness as the ultimate currency and trying to kind of
eliminate outside influences and really think about what is meaningful to me and what will make me happy in what I study. So thank you.
Thank you. The ultimate currency. Many people say about Americans that one of the reasons why levels of depression are on the rise, one of the reasons why
there are so many unhappy people is because Americans have too high expectations and that's not true I disagree with it and the research
disagrees with it. It's not about having high versus low expectations it's about
having right versus wrong expectations. It applies to many areas but one of the
things to understand is that where do we look to gain gratification from our
Is it from, again, getting the next accolade, the next promotion, or that people tell us how wonderful our concentration is, or is it from doing what we want to do?
In other words, being determined by the ultimate currency and understanding that happiness is the ultimate currency. Thank you.
I feel that all this semester, all this year, in fact, I have been trying to, well I've been either going to class or running to lab or just finding some way
to fill up every hour of my day and it seems like I'm constantly running from one place to another and seems like all my life I've been just essentially trying
to fill up every hour of my day and I feel what's really important and what I really got from this is what you said about doing less is more and it's
something I'm definitely going to take, like, keep in mind the next three years I'm here.
Less is more. Quantity affects quality. And we so often wonder, you know, how come I'm not happy?
I have so many things in my life that are wonderful and amazing. And that could be part of the problem
because more is not always better. Not easy to simplify. That's so very important. So very
important the concept of simplicity on the other side of complexity is so hopeful for me because
you know when you grow up in life you add all these variables and it becomes more and more complicated and as the entropy builds up there's a certain frustration about you know not being able
to simplify but when you say at the top of the complexities when you realize the beauty of is realizing that simplicity comes after complexity,
not before complexity. The knowledge of complexity, that's an amazing concept.
So Oliver Wendell Holmes, who talked about the simplicity on the other side of complexity,
and that applies whether it's to ideas. And again, this class, most of it was very simple. And there were no very complicated concepts here.
But many of them are the simplicity on the other side of complexity. the same on an individual level. Very often we go through hardships and our
life is so difficult. We go through a crisis, through a crucible and what we need to do to understand when we're going through that complexity and
hardship and the crucible and the difficulties is that there is simplicity on the other side. Very often all we need to do is hang on, just wait a little bit
longer, and there'll be more clarity, more growth, more development, more joy at the end of it.
You were passing around the mics, and I was like, oh my god, I don't really have anything to say. There's so many people I would never do that, and then you said, trade is not about being fearless, but about having fear and doing it anyway, so I just
threw my pack over the wall. I was like, give me that mic, I'm going to do it,
and it's in my hand, and I'm speaking, so thank you for that.
that's what it's about it's about behavioral change not in theory good
yes you've spoken in the past few lectures about an anonymous world and
about how we would live if our actions were anonymous and I think that knowing what we want and actually pursuing what we want is there can be very
challenging even frightening and it just seems like you really know what you want and have pursued and pursue what you want and I think that's something to
be really proud of and you definitely seem to practice what you preach or teach and I am have an enormous amount of respect for you because of that thank
you there are many things but one thing I really learned from this class is it is
important to focus on what we really really really like to do you said many
times in the class teaching is your calling and I can see how much you're enjoying teaching and it was really inspiring to me so I think I will
remember that and I will keep looking for my calling and what I really like to
do. Thank you. Thank you. Someone with a microphone and we'll get it to you. Anyone
have a microphone? I used to be the kind of person who like ran away from my
problems and I used to try to ignore them until they went away and I don't do that anymore because I know that if I'm unhappy the only person who can do
something about it is me and I need to make a change and this class has given me all sorts of tools to do that, so thank you.
I just wanted to thank you for the idea of the power of commitment because it helped me get my job in something that I want to do, which is journalism versus something that I wasn't as excited about doing,
which was like PR. So I wanted to thank you for that because I decided to jump into it and throw my bag over the wall, and that's why I got it, so thank you.
Thank you.
Yeah.
Hi Niemann fellows. I remember that you talked about when you stretch a muscle
it gets stronger and brought up the idea of the stretch zone and I didn't realize how much stronger I would become when I I stretched myself and did
things that weren't things in my stretch zone and my panic zone I just thank you because I think this class has really been the roadmap a lot of us have needed
to change and become happier so thank you good afternoon everyone I'd like to
first of all say you're great and yeah and also I am a proud educator in the
Milwaukee public school system are there any future educators at the room and
And what you speak of as, well, Albert Vandera and the theory of self-efficacy is so very important.
And anyone who is interested in youth empowerment or education, it's very, very important, number one, to have high expectations for our children, especially children of color.
Because as an educator, I see what Vandera talks about and what Duet talks about,
this diminished sense of reality for these kids that produces a whole other world for them.
So I just want to really focus and kind of stress that, and thank you for sharing that, that it's important to have high expectations for children and for yourselves, of course.
Beliefs are self-fulfilling processes. We so often create the world, our world, and the world of those around us based on our beliefs.
Let's take a couple of more, and then I'll do my quick summary.
Yes.
Okay.
Go for it.
I know this has been mentioned a couple times already, but it's so easy to blame others for our unhappiness or others' actions, or even our own actions for our unhappiness.
but you've talked so many times about what's going on in our own subconscious and how what our subconscious may be doing might actually be preventing our unhappiness
or preventing our happiness rather and it just brought me back to Marvel Collins and how if a student did something wrong she made them go through
the alphabet and say these are all good things about me and it's really been
enlightening to try to think about how am i thinking what am i not doing to others or what
are not what other others are doing to me but what am i thinking that that's preventing me from being
a happier person thank you that's wonderful thank you let's take two more so up there
I guess two things that really stuck with me from the class is the little clip you showed
of the baby learning to walk and just like what you conveyed and that idea of like this baby has no reason to like have a sense of why his falling down should be anything to
be ashamed of and that was just like a very effective way to kind of convey like what you're always saying was kind of learn to fail or fail to learn and that really stuck
with me and also your own willingness to describe your own kind of rises and falls as you went through your own study of psychology and your experiences at Cambridge and Harvard
and just your willingness to be very open about it is kind of empowering like for me is I'm about to graduate and I go forward and kind of maybe don't know exactly what
you want to do and you consider different options and obviously that fear of failure especially when you're coming from a place like Harvard is maybe especially acute and
And it's just you're willing to share those experiences, empowering, at least I feel it,
as I kind of question the choices I'm going to make. So I really appreciate that.
Thank you.
Every day is a beautiful day.
And to be grateful for that somehow makes it easier to go out and try to do things that maybe even we fail at.
And common sense is not that common. and these are all a lot of things I've learned here I already knew but now I
learned it at Harvard great all right let's take one more all right so I'm a
senior and I'm leaving so this is my last lecture class at Harvard and so I
I apologize if this message seems a little more geared towards the undergrads in the class.
One of the things that I'm very impressed with as a large lecture class is that it's so far-reaching as far as the number of people who want to take it and diversity of the students in the class.
But I guess the experience that I'd like to share is that I came into this class admittedly because I value honesty, I will say I took it because I thought it would be a nice compliment
to an otherwise difficult senior spring, and I thought, well, it'll be a nice class to have. And my sophomore year, I had gone through kind of a self-discovery post-depression
that made me kind of value things in a different way. And so I've been using these lessons that I've learned sophomore year, and I thought, well, maybe this class will just be redundant.
It turns out I went through another really difficult time during my senior spring.
And, sorry, I guess what I'd like to relay to especially the undergrads here is that it's very important if you're a freshman, if you're a sophomore, it's not even too late as a junior.
It's very important to prioritize what's really important to you at this school. And let me tell you, it's not the paper, it's not the problem set, it's not getting a full
eight hours of sleep when your friend needs your attention for an hour because the people here matter most and you will miss them. And if you don't spend time with them now, you won't have time to spend with them later on.
So it's very important. Prioritize what is meaningful for you and what you really, really, really want to do at this school because before you know it, it will be over. So, thank you for helping me remember that
and making a meaningful semester.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
Let me summarize.
All of these things you've already mentioned before.
These are not necessarily the most important. These are the ones that, for me, without looking back on my notes, came up.
First, the questions that you ask.
The questions that you ask will very often determine the quest that you take.
And if we only ask the negative questions such as why do so many of these individuals fail,
then we won't see the potential for greatness that exists in each individual. If we only ask how can my relationship be improved,
then we will not see all the wonders and the treasures and the miracle that exists in the person.
next to us. We also need to ask the positive question. What is good about my relationship? What is great about my partner? What is wonderful about myself?
What is meaningful to me? What is pleasurable to me? What am I good at?
Questions start a quest and the kind of quest that they start depends on the
quality of the questions that we ask. The four-minute mile. Beliefs create
reality. Not only beliefs but to a great extent how we perceive reality is what
actually comes true. Marva Collins believed in her students, believes in
her students and miracles happen. Those unteachable ones become extraordinary
because of beliefs.
Remember John Concher's study, once again,
about business school graduates.
Two things distinguish the extraordinary from the rest.
One, whether they were always asking questions, always wanting to learn more,
having that humbleness that's so important for growth and well-being and self-esteem.
And second, they believed in themselves. They had confidence. they had the self-efficacy to succeed and to thrive. How do we improve the belief?
By putting ourselves on the line, by coping, by taking risks, by showing ourselves that we can do it.
Through visualization there are no shortcuts to success, learn to fail or fail to learn.
It is no coincidence that the most successful, extraordinary people in history were also the ones who failed the most.
Whether it was in sports, Babe Ruth, who struck out more than any other player of his time, but also hit the most home runs.
Whether it was Michael Jordan, who described his failures time and time again. whether it's taking the game-winning shot where he didn't make it or practicing over and over again
it's no coincidence that thomas edison the person who has more patents than any other scientist in history is also the scientist who had failed the most time remember dean simonton's
work on scientists as well as artists the most successful ones were also the one who
fail the most. There is no other way to learn. Moreover, if we accept this, if we accept this
growth mindset as opposed to fixed mindset that Carol Dweck talks about it, not only
will we improve more, we will also be happier because then not every experience is a threat
to our ego, to our self, to our self-esteem. If we accept that failure is inevitable, whether
in a relationship there are disappointments and arguments or an individual life or on a national
level no perfect country no perfect person no perfect organization and if you understand that
life is about this as opposed to about this will be so much happier so much calmer and paradoxically
so much more successful the permission to be human there are two kinds of people who don't
experience painful emotions who are they again the psychopaths and dead people i'm so glad
none of you are psychopaths and that you're all alive it makes the class so much better
so much safer you're not going to come out of this class experience the constant high
no one experiences a constant high you're going to continue to have those ups and downs
The only difference, I hope, that you will experience now is that when you experience a painful emotion, you will look at it and say, oh, I'm human.
It hurts. I wish it weren't that way.
But I accept it just like you accept the law of gravity.
Because the law of gravity is as much part of physical nature as painful emotions are part of human nature.
Permission to be human.
We talked about many interventions that work in this class. Most interventions don't work
as we've seen whether it's with a Somerville study or others. Journaling works. When we write,
when we open up, whether it's in writing or sharing with the person we care about,
and it can be a therapist, it can be our best friend, our partner. When we share, when we open up,
we're able to make sense create a sense of coherence in the words of Antonovsky about the experiences of our lives
and enjoy higher levels of happiness it works there are so many treasures of happiness all around us and within us
and the question is do we notice them or do we take them for granted
remember the word appreciate it has two meanings one is to say thank you for something which is a nice thing to do. Again, Sistero called gratitude the highest of virtues.
It's a nice thing to be grateful. The second meaning is no less important.
Appreciate means to grow. And when we appreciate the good in our lives,
when we appreciate the good in our relationship, when we appreciate our partner,
our friends, our classmates, when we appreciate our country, the good grows.
unfortunately the opposite is also the case when we don't appreciate the good depreciates there is
no perfect relationship no perfect person no perfect country the important thing though is
to focus on what is working appreciate it so that it appreciates so many people wonder why they're
not happy even though they have all the things that they want to in their lives why because there
there can be too much of a good thing. Remember my favorite piece of music? Whitney Houston
and I will always love you. Straight ten. Second favorite, Beethoven's ninth. Nine
and a half. Play together, play together, noise. Not nineteen and a half, not ten, not
five. Noise. There can be too much of a good thing. Easier said than done to simplify but
remember that a much better predictor of well-being than material affluence is
time affluence. Simplify, assert yourself, say no at times when it's
appropriate. Find out what you really, really, really want to do with your life
and do it. The number one predictor of well-being, relationships. The number one
predictor of well-being are the intimate relationships that you cultivate now and in the future. There is more than anything else in the world. Yes, even more than a
problem set, even more than an exam, even more than how wildly successful we are
and how admired we are. Yeah, that will lead to a spike in our well-being. Very quickly we'll go back to base level just like the tenured professors went back to
base level, just like the lottery winners and the highly successful individuals who thought they had made it and then went to base level and below because they didn't
know what would make them happier. Well this is what can, one of the things that can make us happier. And to cultivate relationships means to invest in them, to
put time into them to share, to open up. Just like we would invest if we found our
ideal job, ideal workplace. We would start to invest then. Same with
relationships. Remember movies end where love begins. It's about cultivating the
relationship after the screen comes down, after the sun sets. That's where the
investment that's where the return on investment comes our mind can take us
only so far now I know positive psychology pretty well I apply everything
that I talked about here however I really think that if I was not cognizant of the
mind-body connection and applying the mind-body connection to my life I would
be far less happy than I am today. Why? Because I would be compromising on my base level,
God-given, genes-given level of well-being. Because when we don't exercise, it's like
taking a depressant. And then we have to fight our nature. And it's very hard to fight our nature. It's very difficult to enhance our levels of well-being as is. To have to also
fight against nature is incredibly difficult so remember the wonder drug
exercise at least four times a week for 30 minutes if you can if you're interested
do some form of yoga or mindful meditation sitting meditation if not at
the very least breathe breathe deeply a few times a day three deep breaths can
make a big difference. Now is not a bad time to do it. Sleep, when possible eight
hours or somewhere around eight hours a night of sleep and touch. Hug, embrace
an underused sense and so important. Be known rather than validated and again all
of us have the need to be validated. It's not about getting rid of our
dependent self-esteem, but it is very much about first and foremost being known, expressing
rather than impressing. Life becomes so much lighter, so much easier, so much more exciting
when we're about expressing ourselves, being known rather than being validated, whether
it's with our romantic partner, our family, our friends, our colleagues, our class, the
foundation of the growth of intimacy and passion in long-term relationships.
Easier said than done, it's so important. Now I tried to have top 10 but I couldn't, I had to
have one more so you'll have to excuse me. The last one and one that brings
together all the others on so many levels is the one about change. Finally,
Raj, you've been waiting the entire semester just for this. Well, was worth
the wait I hope. There are two types and there are many types but there are also
two types of graduates from 1504 or any other class or workshop that is about
obtaining higher levels of happiness. One that at best enjoys a temporary high
or a nice memory and then goes back down to base level and the second one
that enjoys maybe that same temporary high which cannot last our entire lives but then still enjoy continuous growth throughout their lives.
And the difference, the primary difference,
is whether or not you introduce behavioral changes.
Remember Peter Drucker, what he said whenever people came to him for a weekend seminar intensive. He said on Monday, don't call me to tell me how wonderful it was.
Call me and tell me what you're doing differently.
because in his 65 years of experience working with the most successful,
the most inspiring, the best and the brightest people in the world, what he has found that this is what distinguishes real lasting change from a temporary high.
Don't tell me how wonderful it was, tell me what you're doing differently on Monday.
produce behavioral change now. This is the core of change. What you learned in
this class hopefully is only the beginning. Only the beginning because remember like once again culture study, the people who succeed the most who are
happiest, succeed the most in the ultimate currency in the long term are ones who are lifelong learners, always asking questions, always finding out more.
There are many people with good intentions, many people with good intentions, but good intentions are not enough.
What we also need is the foundation, the empirical, rigorous, scientific foundation of things that work.
And when we know these things, then we pay them forward, then we share them.
In psychology, among the other social sciences and sciences and humanities,
What you got here at Harvard, what you're getting here at Harvard is that foundation that can make the world a better place.
I don't teach this class only because it's fun for me. It is fun for me. Yes, it is very pleasurable to me.
I told you I can't wait for Tuesdays and Thursdays to share what I care about most with you. Yes, it's fun. But I don't just do it because of it.
I do it because I think the ideas of some of the great psychologists that I've quoted and cited and discussed,
their ideas can change the world for the better.
Maslow, back in 1954, wrote,
I'm not only the disinterested and impersonal seeker for pure cold truth for its own sake,
I am also very definitely interested and concerned with man's fate, with his ends and goals and with his future.
I would like to help improve him and better his prospects.
I hope to help teach him how to be brotherly, cooperative, peaceful, courageous and just.
I think science is the best hope for achieving this and of all the sciences I consider psychology most important to this end.
Indeed, I sometimes think that the world will either be saved by psychologists in the very broadest sense,
or else it will not be saved at all, in the broadest sense of psychologists.
That doesn't mean that you now have to go on and get a PhD in psychology or to concentrate in psychology.
but it means to be cognizant, to be self-aware of what is going on in here,
the most wondrous and amazing entity in the universe,
to understand what's going on here and there and here, and how they are connected,
and to share it by being practical idealists. And you can make a difference.
You can make a difference because the One has incredible power. Remember, if you make three people smile and they make three other people smile after 20 iterations
you will touch every single human being on the planet happiness is contagious let me show you
one last video of how happiness and joy is contagious Daddy's going to make you laugh now, ready?
What kind of world they will grow into depends on you.
And it depends on whether or not you first and foremost take care of yourself.
In the words of Gandhi, be the change you want to see in the world. If you want a happier world, be that change.
Oh, the places you will go.
I would like to remind you that every time you go to a place, and very often you will fly to a place,
that every time you go, you will hear something that hopefully will trigger,
hopefully will remind you how important it is to take care of yourself. Because to take care of others, you first and foremost need to take care of yourself.
You know when you fly and the flight attendant says in case of an emergency and the oxygen mask comes down,
first help yourself before you help others who need your help. Because that is the source, the foundation of the golden rule.
it is the foundation of a better world, the ultimate currency.
So each time you go to one of those wonderful places, exotic or otherwise,
remember to simplify.
Remember to take care of yourself. Remember to exercise.
Remember to assert yourself and say no when appropriate.
Remember to cultivate your relationships. remember what it is that is really, really important for you in your life.
This experience, this semester, for me has been extraordinary.
And it was made extraordinary first by the amazing teaching staff that we have.
you have no idea what kind of work what's going on behind the scenes you
have no idea how much how much each and every one of the teaching staff the
Hattieff Sean and Deb and every one of the others how much time they put into
cultivating that relationship with you. How many hours they spent, how much, how
many mindful and heartful moments they spent. So I would like to thank them and
I would like you to thank them for their presence, for who they are. So thank you. Come on, come on.
I'd like to give RTS a little token of our celebration artwork, thank you.
Okay.
Do you want to take your time?
It's my turn. It's your turn.
It's my turn. Thank you.
Quick, quick, quick, quick. Okay, so I actually just want to say thank you to all of RTS for their great work. Thank you to all the students here and Extension students.
Most importantly, I'd like to thank my, no, I'd like to thank Tal.
So right back here, I want to thank Tal's grandparents for surviving, for his parents for thriving, and for you-know-what, yeah, okay.
For you-know-what.
I'd like to thank Tammy for putting a smile on Tal's face, and Sherelle and David for
sharing him with us, and for the opportunity for all of us to be a little more human because of your humanness, so thank you.
We're not the only ones who are intensely grateful to you.
You've touched so many people here this semester, and always, but your students this semester often do thank you notes,
and we've compiled them and found them for you for all the places you go to take with you. Thank you.
That is volume one of the gratitude book where more letters are coming in, so you can still send them.
And finally, it wouldn't be, we want a token for you to always remember this class and this great opportunity something that you we would hope you would use every time you teach
this class in the future i mean no pressure and because you are our king leader and
one more thing one more thank you thank you so much just want to say two more things
I know we're over time. I'm really sorry. Well, one minute.
I want to thank just a few other people.
I would like to thank
Barry Reed, sitting at the back, and the wonderful
crew who are bringing this class to your home, to your computers. And
finally, I would like to thank you.
each and every one of you is an entire world the world in the making in the
making of this world your world our world a better place so thank you and take
Take care, take good care.